Not all heroes wear capes. Some wear overalls.
The Super Mario Bros. Movie is a family, comedy,
adventure film directed by Michael Jelenic.
While working underground to fix a water main, Brooklyn plumbers—and brothers—Mario and Luigi
are transported down a mysterious pipe and wander into a magical new world.
But when the brothers are separated, Mario embarks
on an epic quest to find Luigi.
Mario (voice), played by Chris Pratt.
Princess Peach (voice), played by Anya Taylor-Joy.
Luigi (voice), played by Charlie Day.
Bowser (voice), played by Jack Black.
Toad (voice), played by Keegan-Michael Key.
Donkey Kong (voice), played by Seth Rogen.
The Super Mario Bros.
Movie is a 2023 animated adventure comedy film based on
Nintendo's Mario video game franchise.
Directed by Aaron Horvath and Michael Jelenic and written by Matthew Fogel, the film stars an ensemble voice cast led by
Chris Pratt, Anya Taylor-Joy, Charlie Day, Jack Black, Keegan-Michael Key, Seth Rogen, and Fred Armisen.
It was produced by Illumination and Nintendo.
The film features an origin story for the brothers Mario and Luigi, two Italian-American plumbers who are separated after being transported to
another world and become entangled in a battle between the Mushroom Kingdom, led by Princess Peach, and the Koopas, led by Bowser.
As a result of the critical and commercial failure of
the live-action film Super Mario Bros.
(1993), Nintendo became reluctant to license its
intellectual properties for film adaptations.
Despite this, Mario creator Shigeru Miyamoto became interested in developing
another film during the development of the Virtual Console service.
Through Nintendo's work with Universal Parks & Resorts to create Super
Nintendo World, he met with Illumination CEO Chris Meledandri.
By 2016, they were discussing a Mario film and, in January 2018, Nintendo
announced that they would produce it with Illumination and Universal.
Production was underway by 2020, and the cast was announced in September 2021.
The Super Mario Bros.
Movie premiered at Regal LA Live in Los Angeles on April 1, 2023, and was
released in the United States on April 5 by Universal Pictures.
It received mixed reviews from critics and grossed $1.36 billion worldwide, breaking multiple box-office records, including earning a Guinness World
Record for the highest-grossing film based on a video game, and becoming the first film based on a video game to gross over $1 billion.
It became the second-highest-grossing film of 2023, the third-highest-grossing animated film, the
fifteenth-highest-grossing film of all time, and the highest-grossing film produced by Illumination.
At the 81st Golden Globe Awards, the film received nominations for Best Animated Feature Film, Best
Original Song, and Cinematic Box Office Achievement, a category introduced at the same ceremony.
A sequel, titled The Super Mario Galaxy Movie, is
set to be released on April 1, 2026.
The film explores themes of gorilla, plumber,
villain, anthropomorphism, magic mushroom.
The tone is lighthearted.